A Guide to the Julian Stanley Wise Papers, 1935-1973
Roanoke Public Libraries
Roanoke Public Libraries
Julian Stanley Wise Papers 1935-1973
Roanoke Public Libraries
Wise.VR.1.7
1 box
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information available.
Biographical/Historical Information
Julian Stanley Wise, born in Roanoke, VA, on 13 January 1900, was founder of the Roanoke Life Saving and First Aid Crew, the first volunteer rescue squad in the United States. He was the son of Robert Samuel Wise and Marcella Himes. As a nine year old child, Wise was among a group of spectators who had watched helplessly from the banks of the Roanoke River as two men drowned. Inspired by his childhood memory, he and nine of his co-workers at Norfolk & Western Railway formed the volunteer rescue squad. Wise is also credited with helping communities throughout Virginia and other states to organize volunteer rescue squads. He was also involved in the founding of state and international rescue squad organizations. Throughout his life Wise received many awards and tributes, including a citation from President Nixon in 1973 for his dedication to the rescue squad movement. Wise was captain of the Roanoke Squad for 30 years and stayed on as squad president until 1985. He was married to Ruth Light Wise. Wise died on 22 July 1985 at the age of 85.
Scope and Content
The Julian Stanley Wise Papers contains materials associated with Julian Sanely Wise, founder of the first volunteer rescue squad in the nation. Documents include biographical sketches, documents on the history and organization of the Roanoke Life Saving and First Aid Crew and the Virginia Association of Rescue Squads; personal correspondence, media articles; and certificates, tributes and awards.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged into six series. Biographical materials, Virginia Association of Rescue Squad materials, Roanoke Life Saving and First Aid Crew Materials, Personal Correspondence, Media Articles and Certificates and Awards.
Index Terms
Wise, Julian Stanley; Roanoke Life Saving and First Aid Crew; Virginia Association of Rescue Squads; Roanoke, VA
Contents List
- Biographical Material
  - "Roanoke's Pioneer," No date. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Biographical sketch of Julian S. Wise, author unknown.
  - "Biography of Julian Stanley Wise, " No date. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Biographical sketch, author unknown.
  - "Biography of Julian Stanley Wise, " 16 September 1973. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Biographical sketch of Julian Stanley Wise included in Greenville Emergency Rescue Squad Open House program, author unknown.
- Virginia Association of Rescue Squad Materials
  - Biographical sketch on first organizational meeting of the Virginia Association of Rescue Squads, 12 February 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Author unknown.
  - News release on Rescue Squad Week 1969, Commonwealth of Virginia Governor's Office, Mills E. Godwin, Jr., Governor. 15 May 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Roanoke Life Saving and First Aid Crew Materials
  - Information re: Ruth Wise Trophy (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Poem entitled "Just for Today." No Date. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Roanoke Life Saving Crew Coat of Arms Legend (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Picture, Coat of Arms (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Poem, "The United States Flag." September 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Written by Marcelus A. Johnson, Jr., Medical Advisor to Roanoke Rescue Squad.
  - Announcement of 34th Anniversary of the Volunteer Life Saving and Rescue Squad movement May 1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Announcement, "Forty four Years in the Art and Science of Life Saving May 1972. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Announcement, "Thirty Seventh Annual Convention of the Virginia Association of Volunteer Rescue Squads," 30 September 1972. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Program brochure, "50th Anniversary Volunteer Life Saving and First Aid Crews," 27 May 1978. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Personal Correspondence 1965-1976
  - William J. Lees, Memorial Hospital, Danville, VA to Julian Wise. 27 September 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - William Stewart, U.S. Surgeon General, to Julian Wise. 21 June 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - William Flannagan, Director, Roanoke Memorial Hospitals, to Julian Wise. 29 July 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Richard Crampton, MD, Director, Coronary Care Unit, University of Virginia School of Medicine, to Julian Wise. 1 May 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Harry Rosenbaum to Richard Nixon, President of the United States. 23 June 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fred Walker, Director of Public Affairs, Norfolk and Western Railway Co., to Julian Wise. 14 August 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Richard Crampton, MD, Director,Coronary Care Unit, University of Virginia School of Medicine, to Julian Wise. 25 February 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Richard Crampton, MD, Director, Coronary Care Unit, University of Virginia School of Medicine, to Julian Wise. 27 October 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - R. Earle Glendy, MD, Director of Cardiology, Roanoke Memorial Hospitals, to members of Roanoke Life Saving Crew. 20 December 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Richard Nixon, President of the United States, to Julian Wise. 13 February 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - M. Caldwell Butler, U.S. House of Representatives, to Julian Wise. 16 February 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reverend Dean Kesler, Damascus, MD, to Julian Wise. 2 March 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Stanley B. Kamm, Administrator, Shenandoah County Memorial Hospital, Woodstock, VA, to Julian Wise. 17 July 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Terry Leedom, Carolina Power & Light Company, to Julian Wise. 7 September 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Richard D. Rogge, Federal Bureau of Investigation, Richmond, VA, to Julian Wise. 4 February 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Glenn H. Puhle, President, Virginia Association of Volunteer Rescue Squads, to Julian Wise. 15 March 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Robert P. Adams, Sr., Chief, Garner-St. Mary's Rescue Squad, Garner, NC, to Julian Wise. 9 April 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Richard H. Fisher, MD, Lewis-Gale Clinic, Salem, VA, to Julian Wise. 18 May 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Raymond E. Hogan, Executive Vice-President, Lynchburg General-Marshal Lodge Hospital, Lynchburg, VA, to Julian Wise. 21 May 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Marcellus A. Johnson III, MD, Roanoke, VA, to Julian Wise. 21 May 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - C.S. Elliot, Executive Director, Virginia Baptist Hospital, Lynchburg, VA, to Julian Wise. 21 May 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - William Flannagan, Director, Roanoke Memorial Hospitals, Roanoke, VA, to Julian Wise. 24 May 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Kenneth H. Axtell, ADM Administrator, Williamsburg Community Hospital, Williamsburg, VA, to Julian Wise. 24 May 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Nathan Bushnell III, President, Blue Cross/Blue Shield of Southwestern Virginia, Roanoke, VA, to Julian Wise. 27 May 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Julian Wise to Dr. Norman D. Fintel, President, Roanoke College, Salem, VA. 27 May 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Media Articles
  - "The Rescue Squads Roll On." April 1956, Reader's Digest. Written by James J. Kilpatrick and Charles Henry Hamilton. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Big Results from Little Shots." 26 September 1965, Editorial, author unknown. Register Newspaper, Danville, VA. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Anxious to work with rescue squad." 6 September 1973, Zebulon Record (NC), written by Charlotte Fowler, RN. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Rescue Squad Originator Gets Citizenship Plaque." June 1976, Woodmen of the World Magazine, Omaha NE. Author unknown. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Rescue Squads." 1 March 1975, Roanoke Times, editiorial written by Richard H. Fisher, MD. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Saving Lives." 24 February 1964, Editorial prepared for WSLS TV Channel 10, Roanoke, VA. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Roanoke's Live Saving Crew Gives Demonstration, Using a Dummy." No date., Written by C.R. Hughes. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Plaudits to Blacksburg." No date., Editorial written by Julian S. Wise, Roanoke, VA. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Motive Power Men Started First Aid Crews." 25 May 1928, Author unknown. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Records Magazine, Richmond, VA. Special Edition Featuring Virginia's volunteer rescue squads. July 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Oxygen in Life Saving and Rescue Work.. 1965, Published by Virginia Association of Rescue Squads. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - First Aid Bulletin July 1973, Published by Virginia Association Rescue Squads. Volume XXVI, No. 7. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Rescuer. May-June 1970, Published by International Rescue and First Aid Association, Vol. 14, No. 3. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Green Board to the President." 15 May 1973., Norfolk and Western Magazine. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "A Tribute to Julian S. Wise, Founder of the Rescue Squad Movement." Fall & Winder 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Top Elk Names by Lodge 197." 28 March 1975., Roanoke World News. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Certificates & Awards
  - Man of the Week, Julian S. Wise. Presented at the Hotel Roanoke. No date. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Certificate of recognition for volunteer services, National Foundation, March of Dimes. No date. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Service to Mankind Award. Presented to Julian Stanley Wise by the West Central Virginia District, Sertoma International. 10 March 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Resolution of appreciation to Julian Stanley Wise. Presented by the Council of the City of Roanoke, VA. 18 August 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter of Award of life membership to Julian S. Wise. Presented by N.C. Association of Rescue Squads, Elkin, N.C. 9 September 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Announcement regarding Julian S. Wise receiving John Blair, Jr. Award. Presented by the 192nd Annual Grand Lodge Communication. 12 February 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Certificate of Appreciation for Service. Presented by the National Foundation. No date. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Elk of the Year Award. Presented by Virginia Lodge No. 197, Roanoke, VA. 5 February 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Scroll of Appreciation for Service. Presented by the Roanoke Valley Chamber of Commerce. 29 September 1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)